Guide to the A.B. Guthrie Jr. Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
A. B. Guthrie Jr. Papers
1901-1991
YCAL MSS 60
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
26
(56 boxes)
A. B. Guthrie Jr. (1901-1991), Montana-born writer whose popular Western novels include The Big Sky (1947), The Way West (1949), and Fair Land, Fair Land (1982). His autobiography was published in 1965. In his later years Guthrie became an outspoken advocate of conservation in the West.
Other Storage Formats: oversize
Guthrie, A. B., Jr. (Alfred Bertram), 1901-1991
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The A. B. Guthrie Jr. Papers were purchased in 1993 from D'Archivists. The A. B. Guthrie Jr. Papers Addition consists of three boxes of material donated by Mrs. A. B. Guthrie Jr. in 1993.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 55-56 contain audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
A. B. Guthrie Jr. (1901-1991)
Alfred Bertram ("Bud") Guthrie Jr. was born in Bedford, Indiana, on January 13, 1901. The following June he moved with his family to Choteau, Montana, when his father became principal of the newly created Teton County High School there.
At age fourteen Guthrie began work as a printer's devil for the local newspaper, the Choteau Acantha. He graduated from high school in 1919 and entered the University of Washington to study journalism. After a semester he transferred to the University of Montana because, as he said, "I disliked the climate. Days on end of rain and cloudy skies." While at Montana, he studied under H. G. Merriam, considered the dean of Western journalists, and gained experience by contributing to the regional magazine Frontier.
Upon graduating with honors in 1923, Guthrie went with a friend to Mexico to work on an irrigation project. Soon after Guthrie went to California but failed to locate employment. He returned to Montana in 1924 and found temporary work with the Forest Service, which was conducting a decennial agricultural census. When this job ended, he left Montana to work in an uncle's flour and feed mill in Attica, New York. The mill burned down shortly after Guthrie arrived, leaving him unemployed once again.
In 1926, Guthrie found a position in journalism, working as a reporter on the Lexington Leader in Lexington, Kentucky. His new position and his rapid promotions meant that he felt able to ask his high school sweetheart, Harriet Larson, to marry him. Married in 1931, the couple had two children, Alfred Bertram Guthrie III and Helen Guthrie.
Throughout the 1930s, Guthrie's success as journalist with the Leader increased, but so did his desire to become a serious writer. In 1939 he took a leave of absence to travel to Minnesota with his mother, who was being treated for a terminal illness. While reading many Westerns and detective stories, Guthrie decided to write one himself, later noting that "I was going to write a Western and a mystery but I found out it did not come as easy as I thought it would." The result of this decision was the novel Murders at Moon Dance, published by Dutton in 1943. Although Guthrie later considered it "a trashy piece of work," it did fairly well for a first novel and was also published in England and Argentina.
In 1944 Guthrie received a Nieman Fellowship. During his term at Harvard he met Theodore Morrison, a member of the literature faculty and a former associate editor of the Atlantic Monthly. Under Morrison's tutelage, Guthrie's wrote his first major novel, The Big Sky. Published in 1947 by William Sloane and Associates, it was highly praised and brought him recognition. He immediately began research for a sequel to this popular success, and in 1949 he published The Way West.
The Way West won the Pulitzer Prize in May of 1950. His increasing stature brought him many requests for articles from such magazines as Life, Liberty, Atlantic Monthly, Westways, and the Saturday Evening Post. This income, along with the prize money, allowed Guthrie to retire from journalism and return to Montana.
In 1951 Guthrie was invited to Hollywood to write the screenplay for Jack Schaefer's Shane. After the movie's success, Guthrie went on to write several more scripts. including the Hecht-Hill film The Kentuckian and an adaptation of Bent's Fort that never went to production. His last work in Hollywood was a script based on his own novel These Thousand Hills (1956).
The Big It, Guthrie's first book of short stories, was published in 1960. Guthrie published little in the early 1960s, but his popular autobiography, The Blue Hen's Chick, appeared in 1965. His marriage to Harriet Larson had ended, and Guthrie married Carol Luthin in 1967.
Guthrie now decided to continue his "epic of the West" begun with The Big Sky, producing Arfive, (1970), The Last Valley (1975), and Fair Land, Fair Land (1982). During this period, continuing his early interest in detective Westerns, he wrote a series of books featuring the Western sleuth Chick Charleston (a county sheriff in Montana) and his educated sidekick Jason Beard. The series included Wild Pitch, The Genuine Article, and Playing Catch-up, and won a number of awards, including the Silver Spur Award of the Western Writers Association and an award from the National Cowboy Hall of Fame. Guthrie's last "western entertainment," Murder in the Cotswolds (1989), featured the same characters but was set in the English countryside.
The preservation of the West he loved became a major concern of Guthrie's during his later years. He increasingly accepted public engagements and writing assignments that would allow him to speak out on Western environmental abuses, becoming a "patron saint" for a number of environmental organizations. In 1988 David Petersen edited and published a collection of Guthrie's preservationist writings: Big Sky, Fair Land: The Environmental Essays of A. B. Guthrie Jr.
A. B. Guthrie Jr. died in May 1991.
Scope and Contents
The A. B. Guthrie Jr. Papers document the life and literary career of A. B. Guthrie Jr., known for his Western novels and environmental writings. The papers span the dates 1901-1991.
The register that follows is based upon the finding aid produced by D'Archivists to accompany the collection. The papers are organized into nine series: I. Correspondence; II. Writings; III. Personal Papers; IV. Subject Files; V. Research Files; VI. Photographs; VII. Printed Material; VIII. Audio and Video Recordings; and XI. A.B. Guthrie Jr. Papers Addition.
American literature -- 20th Century; American literature -- West (U.S.); Authors and publishers -- United States; Best sellers; Conservation of natural resources -- United States; Conservation of natural resources -- West (U.S.); Film adaptations; Literary agents -- United States; Publishers and publishing -- United States; Western films; Western stories; Montana -- Biography; Montana -- Social life and customs; West (U.S.) -- Civilization; West (U.S.) -- In literature; West (U.S.) -- Social life and customs; Audiocassettes; Video recordings; Authors; Screenwriters; Abbey, Edward, 1927-1989; Aley, Maxwell; Catton, Bruce, 1899-1978; Ciardi, John, 1916-1986; Clark, Thomas Dionysius, 1903-2005; Clark, Walter Van Tilburg, 1909-1971; Conant, James Bryant, 1893-1978; De Voto, Bernard, 1897-1955; Egon, Ferol; Gries, Tom; Guthrie, A. B., Jr. (Alfred Bertram), 1901-1991; Guthrie, Carol Luthin; Guthrie, Harriet Larson; Helman, Betty; Howard, Joseph Kinsey, 1906-1951; Jennison, Keith Warren, 1911-; Merriam, H. G. (Harold Guy), 1883-1980; Morrison, Theodore, 1901-1988; Morse, Caroline; Prescott, Orville, 1906-; Stegner, Wallace, 1909-1993; White, Theodore H. (Theodore Harold), 1915-1986; Worcester, Donald E. (Donald Emmet), 1915-2003; Brandt & Brandt; Houghton Mifflin Company; McGraw-Hill Book Company; Nature Conservancy (U.S.); Sierra Club; William Sloane Associates, Inc
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Family
    Scope and Contents
    The family correspondence spans the life of A. B. Guthrie. Letters from his parents contain information on Guthrie's life, particularly on his childhood in Montana, and provide insight into Guthrie's writings. Correspondence with his siblings discusses both personal and professional subjects, including Guthrie's own view of his craft. There are courtship letters between Guthrie and his first wife Harriet, as well as substantial correspondence with their children and with his second wife Carol and their two children.
    - Chronological
      - Correspondence, 1902-25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, 1926-27 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
      - Correspondence, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence, 1929-32 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence, 1933-34 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence, 1935-36 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence, 1941-44 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Correspondence, 1945-49 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Correspondence, 1950-62 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Correspondence, 1963-90 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Named Files
      - Mr. and Mrs. A.B. Guthrie Sr. to A.B. Guthrie Jr., undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Mr. and Mrs. (Amy) Erik, 1974-88 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Charles (Chick) Guthrie to A.B. Guthrie Jr. and family, 1941-75 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Charles (Chick) Guthrie to A.B. Guthrie Jr. and family, 1976-81 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Jane Haugen family and A.B. Guthrie Jr., 1949-72 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Jane Haugen family and A.B. Guthrie Jr. (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Family, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Named Files
    - Edward Abbey, 1967-87 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Robert G. Athearn, 1954-61 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Louis W. Attebery, 1976-91 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - James T. Babb, 1949-57, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Jack Barsness, 1958-62 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Ronald Bayly (and Susan Regele), 1980-88, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Dan Bowmar, 1951-79, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - William F. Bourne, 1965-73 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Rex Bundy, 1962-79 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Dale Burke, 1974-77 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - James Lee Burke, 1986-88 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Struthers Burt, 1942-51 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Hughie Call, 1951-69, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Carl Carmer, 1950, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Stuart Conner, 1959-82 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Bruce Catton, 1954-55 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Wayne Chatterton, 1966-91, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - John Ciardi, 1949-67 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Thomas Clark, 1950-91 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Walter Van Tilberg Clark, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Margaret Coit, 1949-50 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Norman Cousins, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Joe DeYong, 1949-50 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Bernard DeVoto, 1947-74, undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Richard Dillon, 1970-75 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Ivan Doig, 1959-82 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Leslie C. Drew, 1971-80, undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Ferol Egan, 1965-72 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Ferol Egan, 1973-82 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Ferol Egan, 1965-79 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Walter T. Edmonds, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Henry Eide, 1966-76 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Richard Etulain, 1970-76 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Malcolm Forbes, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Thomas Ford, 1969-88 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Norman Fox, 1949-61, undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Robert Frost, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Marc and Marnie Gaede, 1987-91 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Rosy Gleason/Circle 8 Ranch, 1950-75 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Rick Graetz, 1975-90 (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Jane Graham - Sage Books, 1964-85, undated (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Gene M. Gressley, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - John A. Hawgood, 1950-57 (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - Betty Helman, 1957-77, undated (Box 5, Folder 66-69)
    - Stewart Holbrook, 1960-63 (Box 5, Folder 70)
    - Firman Andrews Houghton, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 71)
    - Dick House, 1967-86 (Box 5, Folder 72)
    - Joseph Kinsey Howard, 1944-60, undated (Box 5, Folder 73)
    - Richard Hugo, 1980, undated (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - George Jackson, 1962-64, undated (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Keith Jennison, 1950-80, undated (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Dorothy Johnson, 1947-78, undated (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - Grace Jordan, 1954-57 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Joe Jordan, 1947-60 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Joe Jordan, 1960-67 (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - Michael Kennedy, 1959-64 (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - William Kittredge, 1978-87 (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - Henry Larom, 1952-58, undated (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - David Lavender, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - William J. Lederer, 1948-50 (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - Curtis LeMay, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - Dumas Malone, 1950 Apr 20 (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - George McGovern, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - H. G. Merriam, 1947-62 (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - James A. Michener, 1950 May 1 (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Arthur Miller, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - John R. Milton, 1958-67 (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - Mary Moore Molony, 1960-69 (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - Olga Monkman, 1970-73, undated (Box 6, Folder 94)
    - George Montgomery, 1948-63, undated (Box 6, Folder 95)
    - Theodore Morrison, 1945-53, undated (Box 6, Folder 96)
    - Theodore Morrison, 1945-88, undated (Box 6, Folder 97)
    - Caroline Morse ("Callie"), 1965-80, undated (Box 6, Folder 98-99)
    - Ernest Osgood, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 100)
    - David Peterson, 1985-91 (Box 6, Folder 101-102)
    - Orville Prescott, 1947-66 (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - Bill Pronzini, 1981-88 (Box 6, Folder 104)
    - Jack Rittenhouse, 1974-82, undated (Box 7, Folder 105)
    - Basil Rudd, 1954-64 (Box 7, Folder 106)
    - Jack Schaefer, 1978 Sep 22 (Box 7, Folder 107)
    - Arthur M. Schlesinger, 1947 Apr 27 (Box 7, Folder 108)
    - Mary Ellen Sexton/Nature Conservancy, 1979-91, undated (Box 7, Folder 109)
    - Sierra Club, 1966-67 (Box 7, Folder 110)
    - Annick Smith, 1977-78 (Box 7, Folder 111)
    - C.L. Sonnichsen, 1978, undated (Box 7, Folder 112)
    - Wallace Stegner, 1950-77 (Box 7, Folder 113)
    - George R. Stewart, 1966 Jun 19 (Box 7, Folder 114)
    - William Stucky, 1949-60, undated (Box 7, Folder 115)
    - Lawrence S. Thompson, 1950-79 (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - Ross Toole, 1952-59, undated (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - Genevieve Turk, 1965-77, undated (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - Stanley Vestal (W.S. Campbell), 1952 Mar 31 (Box 7, Folder 119)
    - Fred Wachs, 1941-72 (Box 7, Folder 120)
    - Mildred Walker (Schemm), 1947-71, undated (Box 7, Folder 121)
    - James Welch, 1982-90 (Box 7, Folder 122)
    - Theodore H. White, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 123)
    - White Tail Ranch/Wilderness Trips, 1958-62, undated (Box 7, Folder 124)
    - Donald E. Worcester, 1954-80 (Box 7, Folder 125)
  - Chronological
    The chronological file contains routine correspondence from friends and colleagues, fan mail, requests for speaking engagements and letters concerning personal appearances.
    - Correspondence, 1935-46 (Box 7, Folder 126)
    - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 127)
    - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 128)
    - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 129-130)
    - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 131-136)
    - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 137-138)
    - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 139-141)
    - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 142-144)
    - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 145-146)
    - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 147-150)
    - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 151-153)
    - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 154-155)
    - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 10, Folder 156-157)
    - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 158-159)
    - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 160-163)
    - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 164-166)
    - Correspondence, 1961 Jan-Aug (Box 11, Folder 167-168)
    - Correspondence, 1961 Sep-Dec (Box 12, Folder 169)
    - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 12, Folder 170-171)
    - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 12, Folder 172-173)
    - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 12, Folder 174-175)
    - Correspondence, 1965 Jan-Jun (Box 12, Folder 176-177)
    - Correspondence, 1965 Jul-Dec (Box 13, Folder 178)
    - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 179-180)
    - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 181-182)
    - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 183-184)
    - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 185)
    - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 186)
    - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 187)
    - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 14, Folder 188-189)
    - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 190-191)
    - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 192-193)
    - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 14, Folder 194-195)
    - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 196)
    - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 197-198)
    - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 199)
    - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 200)
    - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 15, Folder 201)
    - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 15, Folder 202)
    - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 203)
    - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 15, Folder 204)
    - Correspondence, 1984 Sep 7 (Box 15, Folder 205)
    - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 15, Folder 206)
    - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 207)
    - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 208)
    - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 209)
    - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 210)
    - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 211)
    - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 15, Folder 212)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 15, Folder 213)
    - Empty Envelopes, 1939-89 (Box 15, Folder 214)
  - Agents
    Guthrie's correspondence with agents begins in the mid-1940s. Topics include the sales negotiations for essays, articles, and books; criticism of Guthrie's work; career advice; and encouragement to Guthrie after his failure to win the Pulitzer Prize for The Big Sky. Early letters often contain information on the nature of writings by Guthrie no longer extant. Guthrie's earliest agent was Maxwell Aley, but he soon moved to the firm of Brandt & Brandt, while retaining Aley for certain assignments. Information on Guthrie's lecture tours can be found in the Lee Kedick correspondence.
    - Maxwell Aley, 1945-71 (Box 16, Folder 215-218)
    - Brandt & Brandt, 1950-56 (Box 16, Folder 219-224)
    - Brandt & Brandt, 1957-64 (Box 17, Folder 225-236)
    - Brandt & Brandt, 1965-92 (Box 18, Folder 237-248)
    - Lee Keedick, 1947-57 (Box 18, Folder 249)
  - Publishers
    Publishers Correspondence contains revision suggestions and editorial advice, financial informations, royalty records, and sales statistics. Guthrie's correspondence with William Sloane Associates and Houghton Mifflin is particularly rich in editorial recommendations. While Guthrie batched much of his publisher- related correspondence, he at times separated some files related to particular works. These separated files have been arranged under the individual titles of the works in the Writings series. The "Publishers' Queries" section of this series contains invitiations to Guthrie to write for various publications, and are substantially in their original order.
    - Audio Press, 1989-90 (Box 19, Folder 250)
    - Harper & Brothers, 1948-90 (Box 19, Folder 251)
    - Holiday, 1949-55 (Box 19, Folder 252)
    - Houghton Mifflin, 1949-90 (Box 19, Folder 253-259)
    - Kutenai Press, 1987-88 (Box 19, Folder 260)
    - Northland Press, 1987-88 (Box 19, Folder 261)
    - William Sloane Associates, Inc., 1945-47 (Box 19, Folder 262-263)
    - William Sloane Associates, Inc., 1948-58 (Box 20, Folder 264-268)
    - University of Oklahoma Press/Savoie Lottinville, 1954-59 (Box 20, Folder 269)
    - Publishers' Queries, 1950-81 (Box 20, Folder 270-276)
- Writings, Series II
  Writings is organized in several sections: Books, Articles, Introductions and Reviews, Speeches, and Other Writings. Guthrie's works are arranged chronologically within each section. Under each title can be found manuscripts, correspondence relating to the work, publicity material, dustjackets, and financial records. This is substantially Guthrie's own order for this material. Other relevant information, however, can often be found in the chronological files of Publishers' correspondence. For example, the William Sloane Associates files for 1947-48 contains correspondence bearing on the evaluation, marketing, distribution and sales of The Big Sky.
  Descriptions such as "my typed version" are taken from notecards that Guthrie inserted at the beginnings of manuscript files.
  - Books
    - Murders at Moon Dance (1943)
      - Correspondence, Thayer Hobson, Maxwell Aley, Ira Kent, ABG, Sr., John Stuart Groves, 1940-52 (Box 21, Folder 277)
      - Dustjacket and advertisements, undated (Box 21, Folder 278)
    - The Big Sky (1947)
      - Correspondence, reader, 1947-58 (Box 21, Folder 279-282)
      - Correspondence, William Sloane Associates, publicity. Correspondents include: William Sloane, Dorothy Canfield Fisher, Theodore Morrison, Henry Canby, A.B. Guthrie Jr., Norman Hood, Walter Edmonds, Walter van Tilburg Clark, George R. Stewart, Keith Jennison, Bernard DeVoto, Joseph Kinsey Howard, William Wister Haines, Philip Van Doren Stern, Louis Untermeyer, Charles A. Wagner, 1943-46 (Box 21, Folder 283)
      - Correspondence, William Sloane Associates, 1947-51 (Box 21, Folder 284-285)
      - Publicity--Lists, dustjackets, endorsements, undated (Box 21, Folder 286-287)
      - Reviews--newspaper clippings, undated (Box 21, Folder 288-292)
      - Juvenile edition. Reviews, newspaper clippings, undated (Box 21, Folder 293)
      - Scrapbook in black covers, containing: original dustjacket; for three versions including limited autographed edition, carbons of William Sloane Associates correspondence; original signed endorsement correspondence of literary luminaries; originals of all William Sloane Associates press releases; originals of published reviews; originals of novel excerpts in other publications, 1947-48 (Box 22, Folder 294)
    - The Way West (1949)
      - Correspondence, reader, 1949-59 (Box 22, Folder 295-296)
      - Correspondence, William Sloane Associates, publicity. Correspondents include: Walter van Tilburg Clark, Joseph Kinsey Howard, Eleanor Nichols, William Sloane, Norman Hood and A.B. Guthrie Jr., 1947-49 (Box 22, Folder 297)
      - Correspondence, William Sloane Associates, 1950-51 (Box 22, Folder 298)
      - Correspondence, William Sloane Associates, publicity. Correspondents include: Harvey Bright, William Sloane, A.B. Guthrie Jr., Mark van Doren, Clifton Fadiman, Bernard DeVoto, Norman Hood, and Eleanor Nichols., 1949-54 (Box 23, Folder 299)
      - Reviews, newspaper clippings, undated (Box 23, Folder 300-309)
    - These Thousand Hills (1956)
      - Correspondence, reader, 1956-59 (Box 24, Folder 310)
      - Reviews, newspaper clippings, undated (Box 24, Folder 311)
      - Manuscript, typescript carbon with annotations, undated (Box 24, Folder 312-315)
      - Manuscript, "extra chapters," typescript carbon, undated (Box 24, Folder 316)
      - Mary Moore (Molony), correspondence. Critiques of various manuscript drafts, 1954-56 (Box 24, Folder 317)
      - Promotional material. Advertising mats, order forms, undated (Box 24, Folder 318)
      - Motion picture, studio story conference notes. Mimeographed with annotations, 1957 (Box 24, Folder 319)
    - The Big It (1960)
      - Correspondence. Correspondents include: John K. Hutchens, Rolleen Salla (Saturday Review), Ruth Hills (Esquire), and A.B. Guthrie Jr., 1959-60 (Box 24, Folder 320)
      - Manuscript, "Introduction to Book of Short Stories, 1959," typescript carbon; "Introduction to Comstock's The Big It 9/4/90," typescript original with annotations, undated (Box 24, Folder 321)